Alton B. Parker Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Alton B. Parker Papers 1878-1937 (bulk 1904-1926)
MSS35469
Parker, Alton B. (Alton Brooks), 1852-1926
7,000 items
35 containers
14 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, judge, and Democratic Party presidential candidate. Correspondence, autobiographical and biographical studies, speeches, financial records, legal opinions, scrapbooks, invitations, printed material, and photographs primarily concerning the election campaign of 1904 and Parker's work with legal, civic, and philanthropic organizations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948--Correspondence.; Easley, Ralph M. (Ralph Montgomery), 1858- --Correspondence.; Parker, Alton B. (Alton Brooks), 1852-1926.; Peckham, Rufus Wheeler, 1838-1909--Correspondence.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930--Correspondence.
Organizations
Albany Law School.; American Bar Association.; American Committee for Armenian Independence.; Charity Organization Society of the City of New York. Committee on Criminal Courts.; Democratic Party (U.S.); English-Speaking Union of the United States.; Lawyers' Club (New York, N.Y.); National Civic Federation.; National Council of Religion in Higher Education.; New York State Bar Association.; Sulgrave Institution of the United States and of the British Commonwealth.; Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, Inc.
Subjects
Charities.; Civic improvement--Societies, etc.; Elections--United States--1904.; Law--Societies, etc.; Presidents--United States--Election--1904.
Places
United States--Politics and government--1901-1909.
Occupations
Judges.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Alton B. Parker, lawyer, judge, and Democratic Party presidential candidate, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Amelia C. Parker, and his granddaughter, Mary H. Oxholm, in 1958. Additional items were acquired through gift and purchase, 1960-1971.
Additional Guides
The Parker Papers were described in the Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions 16 (May 1959): 147.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Alton B. Parker are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1852, May 14 Born, Cortland, N. Y.
1873 LL.B., Albany Law School, Albany, N.Y.
1873 Married Mary Louise Schoonmaker (died 1917)
1885 Appointed justice, New York supreme court Chairman, New York Democratic State Committee
1897 1904 Appointed chief judge, New York Court of Appeals
1904 Democratic Party candidate for president of the United States
1907 Elected president, American Bar Association
1919 Dedicated home of George Washington's ancestors, Manchester, England
1923 Married Amelia Day Campbell
1926, May 10 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Alton Brooks Parker (1852-1926) span the years 1878-1937, with the bulk of the material from 1904 to 1926. The collection consists of correspondence, speeches, scrapbooks, clippings, printed matter, photographs, invitations, legal opinions, financial records, and autobiographical and biographical material. The papers are organized into seven series: General Correspondence, Speech File, Autobiographical and Biographical File, Miscellany, Scrapbooks, Clippings, and Printed Matter.
The principal subjects are the presidential election of 1904 in which Parker ran as the candidate of the Democratic Party and his work from 1920 to 1926 with legal, civic, and philanthropic organizations. Material relating to the 1904 election is chiefly in the Scrapbooks and Speech File series. The General Correspondence series includes New York state and county Democratic committee correspondence for 1904.
General Correspondence between 1919 and 1926 features Parker's committee work, organizational connections, and family matters. He was an active member of the Sulgrave Institution of the United States and of the British Commonwealth, National Civic Federation, New York State Bar Association, American Bar Association, Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Inc., Lawyers' Club (New York, N.Y.), English Speaking Union of the United States, Board of Trustees of the Albany Law School, Charity Organization Society of the City of New York Committee on Criminal Courts, Committee for Armenian Independence, and National Council of Religion in Higher Education.
Correspondents include Josephus Daniels, Ralph M. Easly, Rufus Wheeler Peckham, and William H. Taft.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in seven series:
General Correspondence, 1884-1926
Speech File, 1898-1924
Autobiographical and Biographical File, circa 1920-1937
Miscellany, 1878-1926
Scrapbooks, 1882-1926
Clippings, 1892-1934
Printed Matter, 1892-1926
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1884-1926 (Box 1-11)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically by year and therein alphabetically. Correspondence with New York county and state Democratic Party committees for 1904 is alphabetically arranged by county in a separate file at the end of the series.
  - 1884-1900, A-Z (Box 1)
  - 1897 (Box 1)
    - “A-Z” miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Follett, .David L. (Box 1)
    - Follett, .David L. (Box 1)
    - Hill, David (Box 1)
    - Peckham, Rufus Wheeler (Box 1)
  - 1901-1906, A-Z (Box 2)
  - 1907 (Box 2)
    - “A-K” miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - “L-Z” miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Parker, George F. (Box 3)
    - Peckham, Rufus Wheeler (Box 3)
    - Sanborn, John B. (Box 3)
  - 1908-1913 (Box 3)
    - “A-Z” miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Daniels, Josephus (Box 3)
    - Dix, John A. (Box 3)
    - Parker, Mary Louise (Box 3)
  - 1914 (Box 4)
    - “A-Z” miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Hall, Parker (Box 4)
  - 1920 (Box 5)
    - “A-Z” miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Hall, Betty (Box 5)
    - Hall, Mary (Box 5)
  - 1921 (Box 5)
    - “A-P” miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Easly, Ralph M. (Box 5)
    - Betty Hall (Box 5)
    - Hall, Mary (Box 5)
    - Hall, Parker (Box 5)
    - “Q-Z” miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Stewart, John A. (Box 6)
  - 1922 (Box 6)
    - “A-H” miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Battle, George (Box 6)
    - Bixby, George (Box 6)
    - Black, Henry C. (Box 6)
    - Clearwater, A. T. (Box 6)
    - Easly, Ralph M. (Box 6)
    - Gerrard, James W. (Box 6)
    - Hall, Parker (Box 6)
    - Hughes, Robert M., Jr. (Box 6)
    - “K-Z” miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Kellogg, O. U. (Box 7)
    - Parker, George F. (Box 7)
    - Stewart, John A. (Box 7)
    - Thompson, T. Kennard (Box 7)
    - Wadhams, Frederick E. (Box 7)
  - 1923 (Box 7)
    - “A-E” miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Beitler, Harold B. (Box 7)
    - Easly, Ralph M. (Box 7)
    - “F-Z” miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Gramling, John C. (Box 8)
    - Hall, Parker (Box 8)
    - Johnson, Henry A. (Box 8)
    - Kemp, W. Thomas (Box 8)
    - Saner, R. E. (Box 8)
    - Stewart, John A (Box 8)
    - Topkyan, H. H. (Box 8)
    - Wadhams, E. E. (Box 8)
  - 1924 (Box 9)
    - “A-Z” miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Babbage, R. G. (Box 9)
    - Daniels, John (Box 9)
    - Davis, John W. (Box 9)
    - Easly, Ralph M. (Box 9)
    - Fiero, J. Newton (Box 9)
    - Hall, Parker (Box 9)
    - Moore, R. Walton (Box 9)
    - Parker, F. H. (Box 9)
    - Seymour, Origen (Box 9)
    - Stewart, John A. (Box 9)
    - Taft, William H. (Box 9)
    - Veiller, Lawrence (Box 9)
    - Taft, Horace (Box 9)
  - 1925-1926 (Box 10)
    - “A-Z” miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Chapple, J. M. (Box 10)
    - Easly, Ralph M. (Box 10)
    - Edwards, Richard H. (Box 10)
    - Hall, Parker (Box 10)
    - Parker, George F. (Box 10)
    - Stewart, John A. (Box 10)
    - Veiller, Lawrence (Box 10)
  - Undated (Box 10)
  - Incomplete letters (Box 10)
  - New York County Democratic Committee correspondence, 1904, (2 folders) (Box 11)
- Speech File, 1898-1924 (Box 12-15)
  Bound and unbound manuscript and printed copies of speeches.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1898-1907 (Box 12)
  - 1909-1913 (Box 13)
  - 1914-1924, undated (Box 14)
  - 1900-1922 (bound vols.) (Box 15)
- Autobiographical and Biographical File, circa 1920-1937 (Box 16)
  Typescript of an unpublished memoir by Parker and reminiscences by his daughter, with miscellaneous memoranda and notes.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Alton B. Parker's “Memoirs” (Box 16)
  - Character studies by Parker (Box 16)
  - Autobiographical notes (Box 16)
  - Biographers' correspondence (Box 16)
    - “A-Z” miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Hall, Charles Mercer (Box 16)
    - Loring, Arthur G. (Box 16)
    - National Americana Society (Box 16)
    - National Cyclopaedia of American Biography (Box 16)
  - Published biographical articles (Box 16)
  - Unpublished biographical articles (Box 16)
  - Biographical excerpts (Box 16)
  - Biographical notes (Box 16)
  - Biographical miscellany (Box 16)
  - Occasional reminiscences of Bertha Parker Hall (Box 16)
- Miscellany, 1878-1926 (Box 17-20)
  Invitations, legal documents, photographs, financial records, various committee reports, “Gold Telegram” of 1904, and other miscellany.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Invitations (Box 17)
    - 1895-1926 (Box 17)
    - Undated (Box 18)
  - Digest of legal opinions by Parker (Box 18)
  - Court opinions, 1886-1887 (Box 18)
  - Photographs (Box 18)
  - Financial ledgers, 1887, (2 vols.) (Box 19)
  - Financial bills and receipts, 1907-1924 (Box 19)
  - Religious organization reports (Box 20)
  - Committee reports (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous handwritten notes (Box 20)
  - “Gold Telegram” (Box 20)
  - General miscellany (Box 20)
- Scrapbooks, 1882-1926 (Box 21-30)
  Newspaper clippings mounted in bound volumes.
  Arranged chronologically, with some years not represented.
  - 1882-1902 (Box 21)
  - 1902-1904 (Box 22)
  - 1902, May -1904, July 1904 (Box 23)
  - 1904 (Box 24)
    - July-Aug. (Box 24)
    - Aug.-Nov. (Box 25)
  - 1906-1907 (Box 26)
  - 1908-1911 (Box 27)
  - 1913 (Box 28)
  - 1916 (Box 29)
  - 1919-1926 (Box 30)
- Clippings, 1892-1934 (Box 31-34)
  Newspaper clippings.
  Arranged chronologically
  - 1892 (Box 31)
  - 1904 (Box 31)
    - Mar.-Sept., (9 folders) (Box 31)
    - Oct.-Nov., (4 folders) (Box 32)
  - 1905-1909 (Box 32)
  - 1910-1923 (Box 32)
  - 1924, (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - 1925, (4 folders) (Box 33)
  - 1926, (3 folders) (Box 34)
  - 1927-1934 (Box 34)
  - Undated (Box 34)
- Printed Matter, 1892-1926 (Box 35)
  Pamphlets, reprints of articles, and miscellaneous printed matter.
  - Pamphlets, reprints, and miscellany (Box 35)